<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-16"?>
<feed
    xml:lang="en-us"
    xml:base="http://aaronkmurray.com/" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title
        type="text">aaronkmurray.com | Aaron Murray's Blog Feed</title>
    <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=1</id>
    <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=2</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #8: Automatic Image Compression</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Alrighty, let's talk about bandwidth for a moment. Two and a half weeks ago, this site was started as a single HTML page and no external file includes aside from a screenshot. The purpose of the screenshot was to capture a visual change history of the blog so that readers could easily see how the site changed with each post without having to get the &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target="_blank"&gt;code from github&lt;/a&gt; at a certain point in time and view the site locally.
				&lt;p&gt;These images are saved as &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable_Network_Graphics' target="_blank"&gt;PNG&lt;/a&gt; files, which is a lossless image format meaning that all of the original image data is still intact. Unlike &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG' target="_blank"&gt;JPEG&lt;/a&gt; files, PNG files won't mess with the fine details of your image in order to make the file size smaller. This is both good and bad.
				&lt;div class='callout'&gt;
					&lt;img src='img/blog/posts/png-vs-jpg.png' alt='PNG vs JPEG visual comparison. Source: jonmiles.co.uk'&gt;
					&lt;span class='citation'&gt;Image comparing PNG (left) vs JPEG (right) detail&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;The upside is that the screenshots look just like my screen did when I took them. The downside is that the files are bigger than a comparative jpeg file.
				&lt;p&gt;So there are two main actions that should be taken here:
				&lt;ol&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Reduce the filesize via compression utilities&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Create separate thumbnail images and reference those for the previews&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ol&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;For this post, I decided to tackle the compression issue first, even though creating thumbnails would have a bigger effect, simply because the utility that I wrote is more useful universally.
				&lt;p&gt;The utility I just created, called &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog-tools/imgsqz' target="_blank"&gt;imgsqz&lt;/a&gt; (image squeeze for lack of creativity), has the following purpose:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Be executed as part of the "Build" process for this site&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Batch process entire folders full of images to compress them&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Not waste time try to recompress images that have already been compressed (because compression can take a long time)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;I've checked in the tool so that you can look through the source code, but effectively just digs through a folder (and subfolders) looking for PNG files, and then trying to compress them. It keeps track of the files that it has compressed so that subsequent runs are only working on new/changed files. Using it is fairly simple:
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;imgsqz.exe -s=c:\FolderWithImages&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;It's now part of the &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog-tools/blob/master/build/build-aaronkmurray-site.bat' target="_blank"&gt;build script for this site&lt;/a&gt;, so that all PNG images from now on will be optimized before they hit the internet for consumption.
				&lt;p&gt;Here are the results for some of the files on this site:
				&lt;table id='table-png-compression-results'&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;File&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Original Size&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;New Size&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;% Saved&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/screenshots/post-1.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/screenshots/post-1.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;103 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;86 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16.4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/screenshots/post-2.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/screenshots/post-2.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;90 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;74 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;17.7%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/screenshots/post-3.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/screenshots/post-3.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;97 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;68 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;30.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/screenshots/post-4.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/screenshots/post-4.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;88 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;49 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;44.8%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/screenshots/post-5.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/screenshots/post-5.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;122 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;104 KB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;13.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/icons/icon-rss-32.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/icons/icon-rss-32.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1,659 bytes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1,571 bytes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
					&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href='img/blog/logo/logo-1.png' target="_blank"&gt;img/blog/logo/logo-1.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5,025 bytes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3,181 bytes&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;36.7%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
				&lt;/table&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Each KB of savings is worth a tiny bit of load time and a tiny bit of bandwidth. Over time these savings will add up nicely.

			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=3</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #7: Links to GitHub</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Quick post here - I just added links to &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog/commits/master' target="_blank"&gt;each Post's main commit on github&lt;/a&gt; in the post header. Just click on the &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog/commit/b734038a5587fcbae1e8d3e317d7c06c48e18cd7' target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src='img/blog/icons/icon-github-16.png' title='View the code changes related to this post on github'&gt;&lt;/a&gt; icon to see what was changed.
				&lt;p&gt;The purpose is to make it easy to see what changed with each post, but it causes an interesting flow change for "releasing" a post because I need to make a post, and then commit the change, but then edit the post to add the new link to the change on GitHub. 
				&lt;p&gt;
			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=4</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #6: Traffic Analytics</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Now that we've got a way for visitors to subscribe to the site to get notified when new posts happen, let's start capturing traffic stats using &lt;a href='https://www.quantcast.com/aaronkmurray.com' target="_blank"&gt;Quantcast&lt;/a&gt;. 
				&lt;p&gt;After you sign up for a free/basic Quantcast account, you can "start quantifying" your traffic by entering your domain name and generating a snippet of html/js that will ping their servers each time someone loads up your page. Simply slap that down at the bottom of your page for now, and we can start getting a rough idea of traffic stats. 
				&lt;p&gt;That snippet is polite because it does 2 things:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Try to load the tracking script using the &lt;a href='http://davidwalsh.name/html5-async' target="_blank"&gt;async attribute&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href='http://www.stevesouders.com/blog/2012/01/13/javascript-performance/' target="_blank"&gt;speeds&lt;/a&gt; up the responsiveness of the site&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Fallback to &lt;a href='http://www.ehow.com/how_5277834_use-pixel-tracking.html' target="_blank"&gt;pixel tracking image&lt;/a&gt; when javascript is unavailable&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Simple, effective, and good enough for now.
				&lt;p&gt;Note: it will take a few days before the stats for this site show up on Quantcast. 
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/3678669.js?file=quantcast-aaronkmurray.com"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=5</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #5: RSS, Atom, and Build Tools</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Alrighty - creating a new blog these days pratically assumes that readers will be provided with an &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS' target="_blank"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_(standard)' target="_blank"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; feed so that readers can 'subscribe' and get notified when new posts are made. I don't even follow blogs that lack such a basic service feature. 
				&lt;p&gt;Ironically, in the interest of starting from absolute square 1, this blog lacked an &lt;a href='http://aaronkmurray.com/feeds/feed-rss.xml' target="_blank"&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;. That was one of the more challenging pieces that I had to get over mentally when considering doing a blog this way. Fortunately, the thought of losing potential followers was ultimately outweighed by the principle of the project.
				&lt;p&gt;That said, getting an RSS feed up ASAP was &lt;em&gt;very important&lt;/em&gt; to me...even more important than other basics like choosing a database. This leads to an interesting chicken/egg problem however. How will I provide an RSS feed without a database? Am I going to copy/paste even more HTML into an XML file for a RSS feed? What about the Atom feed? Should that be another set of copying/pasting/formatting? Should I just buck up, pick a db, but not mention it until later? 
				&lt;p&gt;Well, given that this site is a fairly unique project, I'm open to fairly unique solutions as we trod down this path. So what is the solution to the feed problem? Parsing.
				&lt;p&gt;Considering my disdain for copying and pasting, and the lack of a database to draw from, I wrote a &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog-tools/tree/master/rss/rssgen/rssgen' target="_blank"&gt;little parser&lt;/a&gt; that would read the HTML from this site and produce &lt;a href='http://aaronkmurray.com/feeds/feed-rss.xml' target="_blank"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://aaronkmurray.com/feeds/feed-atom.xml' target="_blank"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; feeds automatically.
				&lt;p&gt;Running that tool now becomes the first step in the "build" process for this site. That means that the current process for making and releasing a change to this site is now:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Edit this index.html file&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Run my new &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog-tools/blob/master/build/build-aaronkmurray-site.bat'&gt;build script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Commit and Push the changes to &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target='_blank'&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Remote into the webserver hosting this site&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Run my new &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog-tools/blob/master/release/release-aaronkmurray-site.bat'&gt;release script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;While still far from ideal, this is better than &lt;a href='#blog-post-1'&gt;the original&lt;/a&gt; process, and it highlights the important phases in the make/build/release process. In upcoming posts, we'll rely more heavily on these automation points and add many steps to them that handle many of the problems that still need to be solved.
			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=6</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #4: For the Machines</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to assist the machines that will be "reading" the site. 
				&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of simple things that we need to do:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;a href='http://www.robotstxt.org/robotstxt.html' target='_blank'&gt;robots.txt&lt;/a&gt; file for communicating instructions with web crawlers&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; tags to help browsers and search engines&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;You'll notice that this site's &lt;a href='robots.txt' target='_blank'&gt;robots.txt file&lt;/a&gt; is fairly empty. One interesting note is the line &lt;span class='code'&gt;Disallow: /BadBotHoneyPot/&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;I'll go over that in the future, but for now, I'll just say that we'll use that as a trap to identify "bad" crawlers so that we can automatically block them should we choose.
				&lt;p&gt;As for the &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; tags:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta charset="utf-8"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;This meta tag needs to be near the top of the HTML file (before any text).&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;If it is not, or it is missing, then the browser will just try to figure out the character encoding set on it's own.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;You will typically only run across the need to include this once you start dealing with localization of your site.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;More info &lt;a href='http://code.google.com/p/doctype-mirror/wiki/MetaCharsetAttribute' target='_blank'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
					
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="IE=edge,chrome=1"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;This tag basically does two things.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;#1: Tell Internet Explorer to use it's &lt;a href='http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc288325(v=vs.85).aspx' target='_blank'&gt;most modern mode available&lt;/a&gt; (as opposed to IE trying to determine which mode it should run in for best compatibility)&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;#2: Tells browsers with &lt;a href='http://www.chromium.org/developers/how-tos/chrome-frame-getting-started' target='_blank'&gt;Google Chrome Frame&lt;/a&gt; installed to render using GCF instead of their native renderer (Uncommon, mostly to help old slow browsers)&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="author" content="Aaron Murray, akmurray@gmail.com"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Tell the crawler who authored this page&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Tell any users who view your source how to contact you if needed&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;This is more uncommon for sites that have multiple contributors&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="description" content="..."&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;This is a spot where you can describe your site&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Some search engines will use this text as preview content&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Adds some &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Search_engine_optimization' target='_blank'&gt;SEO&lt;/a&gt; value to your site&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://developer.apple.com/library/safari/#documentation/AppleApplications/Reference/SafariWebContent/UsingtheViewport/UsingtheViewport.html' target='_blank'&gt;This tag&lt;/a&gt; is largely useful once you start wanting to have your site look nice on &lt;a href='http://www.nokia.com/gb-en/products/phone/700/' target='_blank'&gt;small handheld&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href='http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2011/11/microsofts-table-sized-tablet-surfaces-in-pre-order/' target='_blank'&gt;giant surface devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;We'll dive deeper into this in the future, but we've got too many bigger fish to fry at the moment&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=7</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #3: Basic Visual Cleanup</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Alrighty, so we have a plan, we've got the code up on &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target='_blank'&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; for the world to see, and we have made a couple small changes to make publishing *slightly* less painful via some scripts to automate a couple of steps.
				&lt;p&gt;Despite my guts screaming out for functionality, something has to be done about the visuals around here. The look is way too 1994, and not in a cool 1994 sort of way.
				&lt;p&gt;I'm going to start attaching a screenshot of the site with each post so that in the future we can easily view the visual progress that is being made. This will be easier than checking out snapshot from the &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog/commits/master/' target='_blank'&gt;github commit history&lt;/a&gt; and running the site locally. In the future this will be harder for folks to do once we get distributed and have various databases powering the content. Fun stuff!
				&lt;p&gt;Back to reality - let's spruce this place up. For all of the newbs out there, the best way to fancy up the visuals on a web page is to sprinkle a little &lt;a href='http://www.w3schools.com/css/' target='_blank'&gt;CSS&lt;/a&gt; love around. Quickly you'll learn about one of the most loved (hated) aspects of web development: browser differences. Luckily there are &lt;a href='http://www.alistapart.com/' target='_blank'&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt; out there to help. For now we won't get into the weeds, but let's just say that for nearly 2 decades we've been struggling with browser differences and there is no end in sight, but at least there is a lot of &lt;a href='http://html5.org/' target='_blank'&gt;hope&lt;/a&gt; that things will get better over the next decade as &lt;a href='http://www.ie6countdown.com/' target='_blank'&gt;older browsers start to die off&lt;/a&gt;.
				&lt;p&gt;Step 1: very basic &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_interface' target='_blank'&gt;UI&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_experience_design' target='_blank'&gt;UX&lt;/a&gt; stuff:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Visually split up the site header from the posts&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Split up the post from each other&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Format certain types of text (&lt;span&gt;like code&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Enable a way to link directly to a specific post&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Add some content to the footer area of the page&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Let's assume that we'll use &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; tags for HTML structure/grouping, and that text should be in either a &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; or a &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; tag.
				&lt;p&gt;Using css, we can add some a style for blog posts that have a &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; tag with a css class of &lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;. These matching tags will be in a different monospace font to make look them more computery. Easy.
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt; .blog-post-body span.code {font-family: monospace, Courier, Lucidatypewriter; } &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;To enabling linking directly to a post, we're going to use the old-school method of using &lt;span class='code'&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; attributes and &lt;span class='code'&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; links. I know this is absurd in the days of &lt;a href='http://www.bloggingbasics101.com/2008/11/what-is-a-permalink/' target='_blank'&gt;permalinks&lt;/a&gt; and SEO friendliness, but we haven't written the permalink code yet, so we suffer for now. I'm doing this for your own benefit here folks - it's my &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PageRank' target='_blank'&gt;PageRank&lt;/a&gt; that will suffer. When we fix this later, it'll also be a great time to talk about the joys of &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_refactoring' target='_blank'&gt;refactoring&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brownfield_(software_development)' target='_blank'&gt;brown-field&lt;/a&gt; upgrades.


			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=8</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #2: Deploying New Posts</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;Already there is pain. Currently, my brand new process when I want to write a new post is:
					&lt;ul&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Open up my &lt;a href='http://www.editplus.com/' target='_blank'&gt;text editor&lt;/a&gt; of choice&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Copy and paste the HTML for a post from my previous post&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Edit the old HTML&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Save and preview the file (testing testing testing)&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Fix my bugs (remember to edit the timestamp, post tags, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Commit the changes to &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target='_blank'&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href='http://code.google.com/p/tortoisegit/' target='_blank'&gt;TortoiseGit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Push the changes to &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target='_blank'&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href='http://code.google.com/p/tortoisegit/' target='_blank'&gt;TortoiseGit&lt;/a&gt; (Manually enter username and password each time in the prompt boxes)&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Remote into the webserver hosting this site&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Pull the changes from github to a local folder&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Copy the files to the IIS folder hosting the site&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Ugh. No fun already. I know we can do better than that. First up, let's automate a couple of those steps.
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a href='http://msysgit.github.com/' target='_blank'&gt;Git for Windows&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href='http://www.thegeekstuff.com/2012/02/git-for-windows/' target='_blank'&gt;how-to&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Select the option for "Run Git from the Windows Command Prompt" so that we can write scripts to do our work&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Make sure that worked (open a Command Prompt, type in "git" and hit Enter&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Clone the github repo to a local directory. &lt;span class='code'&gt;c:\code\git&gt;git clone https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog c:\code\git\aaronkmurray-blog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Make a new Windows .bat file that will download latest code and copy to local website folder:
						&lt;ul&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;cd c:\code\git\aaronkmurray-blog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;git pull https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;xcopy /Y /E /R /V /I "c:\code\git\aaronkmurray-blog" "C:\inetpub\wwwroot\aaronkmurray"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class='code'&gt;REM pause&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Now we can just run that file on the webserver and it'll fetch the latest source from github and push it to the website's folder. 
				&lt;p&gt;Next up, let's take out the step of entering a username/password each time when doing the &lt;span class='code'&gt;git push&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href='http://www.programmoria.com/2012/02/saving-tortoisegit-password.html' target='_blank'&gt;Here is an article&lt;/a&gt; that describes the simple step of creating a batch file, and then running it, enter your username and password, and it creates the file that TortoiseGit needs so that you don't have to enter those manually anymore.
				&lt;p&gt;Far from perfect, but we're taking baby steps here ;)
				&lt;p&gt;Article on &lt;a href='http://longair.net/blog/2009/04/16/git-fetch-and-merge/' target='_target'&gt;git fetch vs pull&lt;/a&gt;

			</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>uuid:37a43e97-e342-4969-b4ae-a24c01f91e8b;id=9</id>
        <title
            type="text">Post #1: The Plan</title>
        <published>2012-09-10T17:10:20-05:00</published>
        <updated>2012-09-10T22:10:20Z</updated>
        <content
            type="text">
				&lt;p&gt;This has been a long time coming. 
				&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to start blogging for about a year now, but have been struggling with figuring out where to start.
				&lt;p&gt;There have been tons of questions swirling around in my head, like: 
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Blog: Roll my &lt;a href='http://www.tandemgames.com/' target='_blank'&gt;own&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.domainofheroes.com/' target='_blank'&gt;site&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.aliensandrobots.com/' target='_blank'&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;? or use seasoned blog &lt;a href='http://dasblog.codeplex.com/' target='_blank'&gt;software&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href='http://wordpress.org/' target='_blank'&gt;heavy community support&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Host: Use a &lt;a href='https://appharbor.com' target='_blank'&gt;cloud&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.heroku.com/' target='_blank'&gt;application&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href='http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/public/sites/' target='_blank'&gt;host&lt;/a&gt;? Use a cheap host that &lt;a href='http://bluehost.com/' target='_blank'&gt;supports simple scripts&lt;/a&gt; for common apps? Host out of the &lt;a href='img/blog/posts/aarons_server_rack.jpg' target='_blank'&gt;server rack in my house&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Platform: Java? .NET? "pure" HTML/JS? &lt;a href='http://expect.sourceforge.net/cgi.tcl/'&gt;TCL/CGI&lt;/a&gt;? Something more &lt;a href='http://rubyonrails.org/' target='_target'&gt;hip&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Audience: Should I be connecting with &lt;a href='http://lostechies.com/' target='_blank'&gt;other developers&lt;/a&gt;? Other small-business owners? Friends? Family? &lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Content: Is this going to be a personal activity log? Professional journal? Or just another tech experiement?&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;As I poured through ideas and wrote down reams of notes, one thing was apparent: &lt;span class='callout'&gt;I was spending a lot of time and effort on the blog but not actually blogging.&lt;/span&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Last night I couldn't sleep. The kid's toy keyboard was "cleaned up" in a way that a key was being pressed repeatedly whenever the air conditioning changed the pressure in the play room. I finally got up to address the situation, and then found myself unable to fall back to sleep. 
				&lt;p&gt;After laying in bed for a couple of hours thinking about the blog, I finally got up to write down my ideas on paper so that I could actually fall asleep. This is common for me: the fear of forgetting an idea keeping me from drifting off into sleepytown.
				&lt;p&gt;This morning I get into work and checked on my RSS feed folder for .NET development. It's been a few days since I checked it, but &lt;a href='http://www.hanselman.com/blog/YourWordsAreWasted.aspx' target="_blank"&gt;this call-to-action from Scott Hanselman&lt;/a&gt; was the final straw. The answer is simply to start blogging now and sort out the details later.
				&lt;p&gt;So what's the plan? Well, the plan is:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Roll my own site/blog from the ground up&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Hosted at my house in my server rack&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Post about all of the changes and more importantly, show the intention behind them&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Make this site &lt;a href='https://github.com/akmurray/aaronkmurray-blog' target="_blank"&gt;publicly available on github&lt;/a&gt; so that everyone can see how it works and see it progress&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Start with a single index.html file and advance the site it all the way through to a scalable, distributed system, from the ground up&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I'd like to think that someone new to the web development craft will be able to use this site, the posts, and the source code history as a guide to seeing what goes on behind the scenes for how to create modern web software. I'm going to start at absolute step 1, and advance steadily through the growth of a real application. 
				&lt;p&gt;I'd love it if you followed me on this journey. It'd be great if you could sign up for an RSS feed to get auto-notifications when I make new posts, but since this is just an index.html file at the moment, you can't. Looks like we've got a lot of work to do. Get ready for a fun ride.
				&lt;p&gt;For now, you can reach me on &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/aaronkmurray' target='_blank'&gt;Twitter @aaronkmurray&lt;/a&gt;. Let me know what you think about this project and what features you'd like to see implemented. Here's a sample of what I have planned already:
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Basics: CSS reset, JS framework, Cloud/CDN hosting&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Javascript: organizing your JS files (custom and 3rd-party), creating your own framework patterns, debugging&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;CSS: responsive design, image bundling/sprites&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Build/Deploy: tools for building, bundling, and deploying the site and assets&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Performance: optimizing response time, payload, client-side caching, server-side caching, web-server and load balancer config&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Debugging: client-side debugging, server-side debugging, error logging, pro-active notifications, self-healing services, system health dashboards and reports&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Testing: js unit testing, server-side testing, integration testing&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Database: choosing a DB, using an ORM (like Entity Framework), writing your own ORM&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Marketing: strategy, considerations, tracking and mining your own site data&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Social: integration with the Majors (Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, Pinterest, etc.), API usage, tracking&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Advanced: client-side MVC, new JS paradigms and protocols for server communication, custom DBMS!&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;As you can see, that is a reasonably ambitious sampling of goals since we're starting with a single HTML page and no code. Let's get cracking!

			</content>
    </entry>
</feed>